Inventory of the Papers of Armistead Mason Dobie 1902 (1939-1956) 1963
University of Virginia, Arthur J. Morris Law Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Law Library
Inventory of the Papers of Armistead Mason Dobie 1902 (1939-1956) 1965
Special Collections, University of Virginia Law Library
MSS 78-2
This collection consists of 15 boxes.
The Papers of Armistead M. Dobie span the years 1902 to 1963, with the bulk of the material covering 1939 to 1956, the years of Dobie's judgeship.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
Armistead Mason Dobie was born 15 April 1881 to Mary Kearns Cooke and Richard Augustus Dobie of Norfolk, Virginia. Armistead entered the University of Virginia and earned three degrees in rapid succession: B.A. in 1901, M.A. in 1902 and LL.B in 1904. He left Charlottesville to practice law in St. Louis, Missouri, but returned to his alma mater in 1907 to teach law and to re-establish the close ties with the University which he would maintain the rest of his life. When Dobie joined the faculty, he assumed the teaching duties of Dean William M. Lile, who was temporarily absent due to ill health. Lile returned, and Dobie remained on the faculty, becoming a full professor in 1909.
World War I claimed Dobie's service in 1917. He was commissioned a captain in the U. S. Army and became an aide to General Cronkhite, with whom he went to France. Before the war was over, Dobie was promoted to major and was made assistant to the chief of staff of the 80th Infantry Division. He was recommended for the D. S. O., and the French honored him by making him an Officier d'Academie with palms.
After the war was over, Dobie returned to Charlottesville, but instead of teaching, he served for a year as the Executive Director of the University drive for the Centennial Endowment Fund. The following year Dobie went to Harvard Law School and begin work on an S.J. D. In the summer of 1922 Dobie studied at Columbia's Graduate School of Jurisprudence and then returned to Charlottesville in time to begin the fall term.
At the time Dobie joined the faculty, the law school program increased from mandatory two to three years. Dobie taught three required courses --criminal law, federal procedure, and probate and administration- - and six electives --Roman law, master and servant, carriers and bailments, code pleading, public officers, and taxation and tax titles. Upon his return from Harvard, Dobie began employing the case method. Young faculty members followed Dobie's lead. With Dean Lile's retirement in 1932, Dobie was appointed dean of the Law School and served in that position until 1939, although ill health in 1936 caused him to relinquish the dean's duties for year or so.
Armistead Dobie wrote a definitive work on law of bailments and carriers, a widely respected casebook and several treatises on federal jurisdiction and procedure, and numerous articles for the Virginia, Harvard and Yale law reviews. In the mid-1930's he was appointed special assistant to the U. S. Attorney General and served for over twenty years. He served as legal advisor to the Conflict of Laws Section of the American Law Institute and was appointed by the U. S. Supreme Court to a committee of 14 to make procedure in federal districts courts uniform nationwide.
In May of 1939 President Franklin Roosevelt offered Dobie the newly created judgeship on the U. S. District Court for the Western District of Virginia with the promise that he might move to the Fourth Circuit when vacancy occurred. Dobie accepted. True to his word, Roosevelt appointed him to the Fourth Circuit Court only six months later.
From early in 1940 until the first of February 1956 Armistead Dobie served on the Fourth Circuit Court along with Senior Judges John J. Parker and Morris A. Soper. Dobie heard almost 1400 cases during his 16 years on the Circuit Court bench and wrote over 450 opinions; only six time he dissented from his colleagues and was upheld by the Supreme Court in four of those opinions.
The most historically significant cases Dobie heard were those involving school segregation. The decisions he helped reached on these cases reflected his firm belief that blacks should have facilities as nearly equal to whites as possible, and his reluctance or disinclination to go against the segregation pattern established by Plessy v. Ferguson.
Judge Dobie officially retired from the bench on the first of February, 1956 in bad health. After many months of complete rest, he recovered somewhat, and on 18 July 1958, he married a long-time Charlottesville friend, Elizabeth McKenny. He lived out the rest of his life at their home in Charlottesville, and he died at 81 on August 8, 1962.
Scope and Content Information
The Papers of Armistead M. Dobie span the years 1902 to 1963, with the bulk of the material covering 1939 to 1956, the years of Dobie's judgeship. The first three boxes contain general correspondence which is primarily of biographical interest, although there are some items, especially the 1939 letters from President Franklin D. Roosevelt, and Senators Carter Glass, and Harry Byrd, that have historical value. The correspondence with Judges John J. Parker and Morris A. Soper in the general files, as well as in the court materials, yield very little information about the cases the three were considering. Other correspondents who wrote Dobie one or two letters of interest were Felix Frankfurter, Stanley Reed, Roscoe Pound, Samuel Williston, Manton Davis and many former University classmates and students. The general correspondence files were kept alphabetically by correspondent's name or, occasionally, by subject, and within the alphabetical division the correspondence is arranged chronologically. Following the correspondence are four notebooks of mimeographed "textbooks" from Dobie's graduate studies at Harvard and teaching at Virginia in the 1920s.
Boxes four and five contain drafts of speeches arranged alphabetically by title or subject. Boxes six through fifteen contain court materials that include records, briefs, and correspondence for a small percentage of the cases Dobie heard. There are few notes and drafts or copies of the opinions he wrote. There are several folders on the Davis v. County School Board of Prince Edward for both the 1951 and 1955 hearings; also of interest is Judge Waties Waring's dissenting opinion on Davis' "sister" case, Briggs v. Elliott. The cases are arranged chronologically are followed by a box containing the dockets for the Fourth Circuit from 1948 to 1956.
Boxes six through fifteen contain court materials that include records, briefs, and correspondence for a small percentage of the cases Dobie heard. There are few notes and drafts or copies of the opinions he wrote. There are several folders on the Davis v. County School Board of Prince Edward for both the 1951 and 1955 hearings; also of interest is Judge Waties Waring's dissenting opinion on Davis' "sister" case, Briggs v. Elliott. The cases are arranged chronologically are followed by a box containing the dockets for the Fourth Circuit from 1948 to 1956.
Box fifteen contains notebooks regarding the work of the U.S. Supreme Court Advisory Committee on Rules of Civil Procedure and of a committee studying the jury system.
Contents List
- General Correspondence A-L 1935-1957, 11 folders (Box 1)
- General Correspondence M-Y 1935-1957, 10 folders (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous Class Notes and Quizzes 1902-1928, n.d. (Box 2)
- Notes on the Opera: Questions AMD submitted for the radio show "Texaco's Opera Quiz" [ca. 1940-1950] (Box 2)
- Research Notes 1947, n.d. (Box 2)
- Research Notes: Judges in Virginia 1947-1951 (Box 3)
- Willliam H. White Lecture Series: District Judges in Virginia before the Civil War [ca. 1947] (Box 3)
- Newspaper Clippings re AMD 1932-1963 (Box 3)
- Administrative Law-Notes [1921] (Box 3)
- History of the Law-Notes 1921 (Box 3)
- Sales: Bound Class Notebooks 1921 (Box 3)
- O.W. Holmes, Collected Legal Papers [ca. 1921], Mimeographed copy in cardboard binder (Box 3)
- R. Pound, Readings in Roman Law and the Civil Law and Modern Codes as Developments Thereof, Part II [ca. 1921], Mimeographed copy in cardboard binder (Box 3)
- A. M. Dobie, Writs [ca. 1921], Mimeographed copy in cardboard binder (Box 3)
- Speeches, Articles, etc. A-F 1910-1956, 7 folders (Box 4)
  Subjects include: Alumni Address, American Legion, Armistice Day, New York Bar Association Address P. Barringer, G. B. Battle, J. C. Battle, Confederacy, Clark Hall, Conflict of State and Federal Judicial Power, Democratic Convention, Geo. B. Eager, Education, C. Glass G. Glenn
- Speeches, Articles, etc. H-Z 1922-1950, 14 folders (Box 5)
  Subjects include: Honor System, Harvard Law Review, Canada Dry "Information Please," Jurisdiction of the Supreme Court, "A Judge Judges Judges," Judicial Opinions, John C. Knox, "Law and Language," Dr. Lambeth, Robert E. Lee, "Law and Morals," McConnell Monument, Raleigh C. Minor, President Newcomb, Judge Northcott, General Pershing, Phi Delta Pi, Pre-Trial Practice, Raven Society, Roosevelt, "Succesful Justice," T.I.L.K.A., Tradition, "Spirit of Virginia," Virginia Law Review, George Wythe, Richard H. Wilson, W.H. White Portrait, "The Young Lawyer"
- Family Life Insurance Company v. John M. Daniel
  - Records and Briefs 1948 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence 1948 (Box 6)
  - Dissenting Opinion by AMD 1948 (Box 6)
- Brooks Transportation Co. v. U.S. and Interstate Commerce Commission
  - Records and Briefs 1950, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Correspondence 1950-1951 (Box 6)
- Coin Machine Acceptance Corp. v. Paul J. Yaeger 1950 (Box 6)
  Motion
- Harold R. Love and U.S. v. D. E. Rippotoe, M. M. Rippotoe, Ruth Jackson, and Frank B. David 1950 (Box 6)
  Notice of Motion
- Industrial Capital Corp. v. Tygart Valley Wood Products Corp. 1950 (Box 6)
  Opinion
- Norfolk Southern Bus v. U.S. and Interstate Commerce Commission
  - Records and Briefs 1950 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence 1950 (Box 7)
  - Opinion by AMD 1950 (Box 7)
- Oltie W. Kennedy v. U.S. 1950 (Box 7)
  Records and Briefs
- Panagiotis Christofis et al. for Mandamus 1950 (Box 7)
  Correspondence and Opinion
- Robert W. Hart and Ellen Brown Hart v. U.S. 1950 (Box 7)
- Constance Carter v. the School Board of Arlington County 1950-1951 (Box 7)
  Records, Briefs, Opinions, Correspondence
- Henry G. Bartson v. Harry D. Friedman 1950-1951 (Box 7)
- The Alabama Great Southern Railroad Co. v. U.S. 1951 (Box 7)
- Alexandria, Barcroft, and Washington Transit Co. v. U.S. 1951, 2 folders (Box 7)
- Alexandria, Barcroft, and Washington Transit Co. v. U.S.-Correspondence 1951 (Box 7)
- Andrew A. Kramer v. U.S. 1951 (Box 7)
  Records, Briefs, Correspondence
- Charles C. Bartoli v. U.S. 1951 (Box 7)
- Consolidated Gas Electric Light and Power Company v. Penn. Water and Power Co. 1951 (Box 8)
- County Board of Arlington v. U.S.
  - Records and Briefs 1951, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Correspondence 1951 (Box 8)
- Craig Kugel v. Alfred Altschul 1951 (Box 8)
- Dorothy E. Davis, et al v. Prince Edward County School Board
  - Records and Briefs 1951 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence 1951 (Box 8)
- Earl T. Davis v. Clifton B. Cates 1951 (Box 8)
- George N. Mas and Frank M. Mas v. William Coleman 1951 (Box 8)
- Harry Briggs Jr., et al v. R. W. Elliott, Chairman, et al
  - Records and Briefs 1951 (Box 8)
  - Dissenting Opinion by Judge J. Waties Waring 1951 (Box 8)
- Jesse Butler v. Mary A. Thompson
  - Records and Briefs 1951 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence 1951 (Box 8)
- Local 33B United Marine Division of I.L.A. v. Battle
  - Records and Briefs 1951 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence 1951 (Box 9)
- Mount, Trustee v. Norfolk Savings and Loan 1951 (Box 9)
  Correspondence
- Mrs. Mae Owens Case v. State of Maryland 1951 (Box 9)
- National Labor Relations Boards v. Jegalock Fasteners, Inc. 1951 (Box 9)
- Pless v. U.S. 1951 (Box 9)
- Stewart-Warner Corp. v. National Labor Relations Board 1951 (Box 9)
- Virginia State Conference of Branches of the N.A.A.C.P. v. City of Richmond
  - Records and Briefs 1951 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence 1951 (Box 9)
- Walter J. Kozdron-Petition for Writ of Mandamus; Correspondence 1951 (Box 9)
- National Labor Relations Board v. Pugh and Barr, Inc. 1951-1952, 2 folders (Box 9)
- Brooks Transportation Co. v. U.S. and Interstate Commerce Commission
  - Records and Briefs 1951-1952, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Correspondence 1951-1952 (Box 9)
- Clavin C. Upton, Jr. v. U.S. 1952 (Box 9)
- Emmett Haydon Bozell v. U.S. 1952 (Box 9)
- (F) 15.6136 Acres in Arlington County v. U.S. 1952 (Box 9)
- George A. Meyers v. U.S. 1952 (Box 9)
- Harold Bernstein v. U.S. 1952 (Box 9)
- Houff Transfer, Inc. v. U.S. and Interstate Commerce Commission
  - Records and Briefs 1952, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Correspondence 1952 (Box 9)
- Jerome Weiss v. Loyal M. Haynes 1952 (Box 9)
  Records and Correspondence
- National Labor Relations Board v. Coca-Cola Bottling Co. of Asheville, N.C. 1952 (Box 10)
- National Labor Relations Board v. Collier Construction Co. 1952 (Box 10)
- National Labor Relations Board v. Pepsi-Cola Parkensburg Bottlers, Inc. 1952 (Box 10)
- National Labor Relations Board v. Roger Williams Shirt Corp. n.d. [1952] (Box 10)
  Letter
- National Labor Relations Board v. Tec. Optical Products Corp. 1952 (Box 10)
- Robert Henry Bugg v. Seaboard Air Line Railroad Co. 1952 (Box 10)
  Brief and Memorandum
- Samuel Kelley v. U.S. 1952 (Box 10)
- Smith's Transfer and Co. v. U.S. and Interstate Commerce Commission 1952, 2 folders (Box 10)
- U.S. ex rel Weiss v. Haynes 1952 (Box 10)
- U.S. v. Jack Court 1952 (Box 10)
- William H. Ward v. U.S. 1952 (Box 10)
- U.S. v. Wayman C. Hamilton 1952-1953 (Box 10)
- Anna Mae Allen v. Southern Railway Co.
  - Records and Briefs 1953, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Correspondence 1953 (Box 10)
- Badgett Trucking Co. v. U.S. 1953 (Box 10)
- Chesapeak and Ohio Railway Co.: I.C.C. Reports 1953 (Box 10)
- Earl T. Ellis v. Clifton B. Cates 1953 (Box 11)
- Edward D. Shaver v. Richmond, Fredericksburg and Potomac Railroad Co.-and R. H. Bugg et al. vs, Seaboard Airline Railroad Co. 1953 (Box 11)
- Henry Heil and J. Henry v. Orla E. Watson and Telescope Carts 1953 (Box 11)
- James E. Pythress v. Frank Pace, Jr. 1953 (Box 11)
- Meacham Corp v. U.S. 1953 (Box 11)
- Ralph H. Witt v. William C. Merrill 1953 (Box 11)
- Robert Henry Bugg v. Seaboard Airline Railroad Co.
  - Records and Briefs 1953 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence 1953 (Box 11)
- Samuel Cummins v. Commissioner of Internal Revenue 1953 (Box 11)
- United Fuel Gas Co. v. Public Service Commission 1953 (Box 11)
- U.S. v. C. W. Sullivan, M. L. Silver Farb and C. E. Heath 1953 (Box 11)
- U.S. v. James Russell McGregor 1953 (Box 11)
- Badgett Trucking Co. v. U.S.
  - Records and Briefs 1954 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence 1954 (Box 11)
  - Opinion by AMD 1954 (Box 11)
- Badgett Trucking Co. v. U.S. and W. Va. Motor Truck Association v. Public Service Commission
  - Correspondence 1954 (Box 11)
  - Pre-trial Conference Transcript 1954 (Box 11)
- Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Co. vs, Henry L. Burton 1954 (Box 11)
  Brief
- Appeal of Edmund C. Fletcher on a charge of Criminal Contempt 1954 (Box 11)
- Frank M. Ellison, Jr. v. the Space River Coal Co. 1954 (Box 11)
- The Jewel Shop of Abbeville, S.C. v. R. C. Pitts 1954 (Box 11)
- John L. Greene v. Charles R. Fenwick
  - Records and Briefs 1954 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence 1954 (Box 12)
  - Opinion 1954 (Box 12)
- Samuel R. Beard v. U.S. 1954 (Box 12)
  Records, Briefs, and Correspondence
- Seaboard Airline Railroad Co. v. United States and Interstate Commerce Commission 1954 (Box 12)
- Seaboard Airline Railroad Co. v. U.S. 1954 (Box 12)
- Seaboard Airline Railroad Co. v. U.S. 1954 (Box 12)
- United States v. E.L. Klingstein 1954 (Box 12)
- U.S. v. Joseph C. Dunford 1954 (Box 12)
- United States v. One 1950-1951 Ford, Van Type One and One-half Ton Truck 1954 (Box 12)
- Washington Coca-Cola Bottling Works Inc. v. National Labor Relations Board 1954 (Box 12)
- West Virginia Motor Trucking Association v. Public Service Commission of W. Va.
  - Records and Briefs 1954 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence 1954 (Box 12)
  - Opinions, one by AMD 1954, Handwritten draft and carbon (Box 12)
- Wilby Kincey Service Corp. v. Sherry Wilson 1954 (Box 12)
- Barton Duer and Koch Paper Co. v. Federal Trade Commission 1955 (Box 12)
- Bettie Low McCoy v. U.S. 1955 (Box 12)
  Records
- Director of the U.S. Bureau of Mines v. Three Fork Coal Co. 1955 (Box 12)
- Dorothy E. Davis v. Prince Edward County School Board 1955 (Box 12)
- Dorothy E. Davis et al. v. Prince Edward County Board 1955 (Box 12)
- E. I. DuPont de Nemours Co. v. Leo Hall 1955 (Box 13)
- Frank Ellison, Jr. v. Spruce River Coal Co. 1955 (Box 13)
- Group of Boston and Providence Railroad Corp. Stockholders v. Interstate Commerce Commission
  - Records and Briefs 1954-1955, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Correspondence 1954-1955 (Box 13)
- Harry Briggs, Jr. et al. v. R. W. Elliott et al
  - Records and Briefs 1955 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence 1955 (Box 13)
- Helen Clyburn, et al. v. Carolina Mining and Exploration Co. 1955 (Box 13)
- Hillard Saunders v. U.S. 1955 (Box 13)
- Ivan M. Halt v. Commissioner of Internal Revenue 1955 (Box 13)
  Record
- John Wesley Hamman v. U.S. 1955 (Box 13)
- Junius Irving Scales v. U.S. 1955 (Box 13)
- Leonard Sykes, Jr. v. U.S. 1955 (Box 13)
- Leroy B. Frazier, Jr. et al. v. Board of Trustees of University of North Carolina
  - Records and Briefs 1955 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence 1955 (Box 14)
- Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Co. v. Albert A. Shugler 1955 (Box 14)
- Norvin Rieser, et al. v. Baltimore and Ohio Railway Company 1955 (Box 14)
- Robins Paper Co. v. Federal Trade Commission 1955 (Box 14)
- Sarah A. Walker v. Harry A. L. Baker 1955 (Box 14)
- S. L. Gardner v. Glens Falls Indemnity Co. 1955 (Box 14)
- United States v. Coley Roby Johnson 1955 (Box 14)
- Annie Mary Timmons v. Commissioner of Internal Revenue 1956 (Box 14)
- Belden R. Reap, Sr. v. Stephen James 1956 (Box 14)
- Dorothy E. Davis et al. v. Prince Edward County School Board 1956 (Box 14)
- Evangelos Papanikolaou v. Atlantic Lines 1956 (Box 14)
- John Sakkas v. V. Goulandris 1955 (Box 14)
- Smith v. Biggs 1955 (Box 14)
- U.S. v. Carl V. Wacker and Norman Bebik 1956 (Box 14)
- United States v. Kramer 1956 (Box 14)
  Notes
- William H. Jackson v. U.S. District Court, Baltimore, Md. 1956 (Box 14)
- Albert Jefferson Lawson, Bankruptcy No. 575
  - Records 1956-1957 (Box 14)
  - Records and Briefs 1956-1957 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence 1956-1957 (Box 14)
- Dockets for the Fouth Circuit Cout of Appeals 1948-1956 (Box 14-15)
- Condemnation Rule 1947-1948 (Box 14-15)
- Order Amending a Rule, Fourth Circuit Court of Appeals 1953 (Box 14-15)
- U.S. Supreme Court Advisory Committee on Rules of Civil Procedure. Tentative Draft III 1936, 1 three-ring notebook (Box 14-15)
- U.S. Supreme Court Advisory Committee on Rules of Civil Procedure. Tentative Draft II 1936, 1 three-ring notebook (Box 14-15)
- U.S. Supreme Court Advisory Committee of Rules of Civil Procedure-Report 1937, 1 three-ring notebook (Box 14-15)
- Judicial Conference of the U.S. Committee on the Operation of the Jury System. The Jury System of the Federal Courts. 1960, 1 three-ring notebook (Box 14-15)
  Preliminary Draft